# Abhrajit Laskar

CONTACT Information

Ph.D. Student in Theoretical Physics Institute of Mathematical Sciences CIT Campus, Tharamani Chennai-600113, India Phone: 91 44 2254 3116
Fax: 91 44 2254 1586
E-mail: abhra@imsc.res.in
Homepage: GitHub Page

RESEARCH INTERESTS Active Soft Matter: Theory and Simulation in close collaboration with experiment. I use relevant statistical mechanics tools and numerical techniques to investigate non-equilibrium collective dynamics, assembly of active colloids, microswimmers and synthetic phoretic particles in viscous fluid.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 1. Abhrajit Laskar, R Adhikari. Instabilities and oscillations of an elastic filament driven by an active colloid. 2015. In preparation.
- 2. <u>Abhrajit Laskar</u>, R Adhikari. **Brownian microhydrodynamics of active filaments**. *Soft Matter*. 2015. Journal Link. Cover page image.
- 3. Abhrajit Laskar, Rajeev Singh, Somdeb Ghose, Gayathri Jayaraman, PB Sunil Kumar, R Adhikari. Hydrodynamic instabilities provide a generic route to spontaneous biomimetic oscillations in chemomechanically active filaments. Nature, Scientific reports. 2013. Journal Link.
- 4. G Jayaraman, S Ramachandra, S Ghose, <u>Abhrajit Laskar</u>, M Bhamla, PB Sunil Kumar and R Adhikari Motility of Active Filaments due to Spontaneous Flow-Symmetry Breaking. *Physical Review Letters* 109, 158302. 2012. Journal Link.

### Reference

• Prof. Ronojoy Adhikari (Supervisor)

Institute of Mathematical Sciences, Chennai, India Email-id: rjoy@imsc.res.in

• Prof. P. B. Sunil Kumar

Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology Madras

Email-id: sunil@iitm.ac.in

#### **EDUCATION**

Integrated Ph.D ( 2009 - present )

Institute of Mathematical Sciences, Chennai, India

- Master's Thesis : Instability in Lattice Structure of Micro-organism
- Supervisor : Prof. Ronojoy Adhikari

## Bachelor of Sciences ( 2006 - 2009 )

Ramakrishna Mission Vidyamandira, University of Calcutta, West Bengal, India

• Major: Physics (qualified in 2009)

• Minors: Chemistry and Mathematics (qualified in 2008)

# Computational Skill

• Programming and Mark-up Languages

**Proficient:** C, C++, Cython, Python

Familiar: Fortran

• Software

Proficient: MATLAB
Familiar: MATHEMATICA

• Visualization

**Proficient:** Open-Dx, Paraview

Familiar: Povray

# TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE

- 1. Numerical methods for Stokes Flow
- 2. Monte-Carlo Simulation
- 3. Lattice Boltzmann Method

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

1. Classical Mechanics (Undergraduate course)

Teaching Assistant IMSc Sept. 2011 - Dec. 2011

2. Statistical Mechanics (Undergraduate course)

Teaching Assistant IMSc Jan. 2014 - Apr. 2014

### AWARDS

- Poster presentation award in Compflu, 2014, JNCASR. Won 2nd prize in poster presentation and a five minute teaser talk.
- Joint Entrance Screening Test 2009 after Bachelors. Ranked 34, securing 98.56 percentile. Got offer from four research institutes for integrated course.
- Joint Admission Test For M.Sc. 2009. Ranked 42.
- National Graduate Physics Examination 2008-2009 (within national 1%).
- Secured 34th position in Physical Science, Junior Research Fellowship (NET CSIR) 2011 December.

## MISCELLANIOUS ACTIVITIES

Conference, Workshop and School attended

- SERC Non-linear Dynamics winter school, Delhi University, India, Dec, 2009
- Gravitation and Cosmology School, HRI, Allahabad, India June, 2010
- Soft Condensed Matter School, SNBNCBS, Kolkata, India, Dec. 2010
- Unifying Concepts of Material, JNCASR, Bangalore, India, Jan, 2012
- Statistical Mechanics School, RRI, Bangalore, India, April, 2012
- Discrete Simulation of Fluid Dynamics, JNCASR, Bangalore, India, July, 2012
- Bayesian inference workshop, Bayes by the bay, Pondicherry, India, January, 2013
- Poster presentation, Conference On Condensed Matter And Biological Systems (CCMB13), BHU, Varanasi, India, January, 2013
- Poster presentation, Diversity and Complexity: Realm of Today's Statistical Physics, SINP, Kolkata, India, January, 2013
- Statistical Mechanics School, RRI, Bangalore, India, April, 2013
- Poster presentation, Summer School Fundamental Problems in Statistical Physics XIII, Leuven, Belgium, June, 2013
- Complex Fluids-2013, IITD, Delhi, India, December, 2013
- Poster presentation and local organiser, SMYIM, Pondicherry, January, 2014
- Poster presentation, SMYIM-2, Pondicherry, December, 2014
- Poster presentation, Complex fluids-2014, JNCASR, Bangalore, December, 2014
- Talk presentation, New Colloids discussion meeting, RRI, Bangalore, India, July, 2015
- Poster presentation, Non-equilibrium collective dynamics-2015, Potsdam, Germany, Oct, 2015

More Information More information and auxiliary documents can be found at Git-Hub Page.